The discovery by Copernicus that the
Earth rotated round the Sun radically
altered humankind's perception of the
universe.
Other astronomers supported him.
Galileo found himself arraigned before
the Inquisition for such heresy.
He later recanted, but the seeds of
doubt had been sown.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Some philosophers, too, began to reject
the established geocentric doctrine.
In Italy, Giordano Bruno fell foul of
the Inquisition for publishing his
dialogues on cause, principles, and
unity.
Unlike Galileo, he refused to recant.
He was burnt at the stake in 1600.
But science and religious philosophy
were drawing closer together.
No arts, no letters, no society.
And which is worst of all, continual
fear and danger of violent death.
And the life of man, solitary, poor,
nasty, brutish, and short.
In 1640, Thomas Hobbes had fled to
France.
There, for a time, he became tutor to
the future Charles II.
Hobbes' ideal ruler was, like the
Stuarts, an absolute monarch whose
function was to keep the peace and
preserve order.
Two years later, King Charles I and his
parliament went to war.
This conflict was to shape Hobbes'
political thinking, and in 1651, [music]
he penned his greatest work, Leviathan.
>> The experience of the English Civil War
and also the study of Thucydides'
History of the Peloponnesian War, which
Hobbes translated,
uh shaped Hobbes' thinking about
politics to the extent that
it brought home to him,
in a way that
few political thinkers really have it in
the forefront of their minds, that the
stakes in political thinking and
political practice are very high.
And if things go politically very wrong,
then the consequences
are, like, extreme misery for virtually
everybody.
>> There were other influences.
Hobbes' idea of a social contract
between the ruler and the citizen owes
much [music] to Machiavelli, Richard
Hooker, and Hugo Grotius.
Hobbes followed Grotius' idea that there
was a natural law, which was based on
man's nature as a social animal.
Hobbes was also fascinated by why men go
to war and what inclines them to peace.
Every man has the right to use his own
power.
Liberty is the absence of obstacles to
achieving this.
But in times of emergency, the citizen
should relinquish his rights to the
ruler in the national interest.
So, political obligation rests upon a
moral obligation.
Hobbes later added a further obligation
upon all citizens.
A simple obedience in all [music] things
wherein their obedience is not repugnant
to the laws of God.
Cogito, ergo sum.
I think, therefore I am.
Most people are familiar with
Descartes's famous dictum.
He arrived at this by a policy of
doubting things in general.
His Discourse on Method set out four
rules that all pursuit of knowledge
should follow.
I am.
I exist is necessarily true whenever I
utter it or conceive it in my mind.
But Descartes arrives at his conclusions
by a process of rigorous
self-examination.
His system depends upon what is evident
to the individual.
An idea is whatever is in our mind when
we conceive a thing.
Pierre Gassendi raised many objections
to Descartes's Meditations.
>> Gassendi's objections, the fifth
objections, really are an extraordinary
document. They're in a way
um they're the most interesting
objections precisely because they are
the objections of a philosopher who is
coming from a point that was entirely
different from Descartes's.
>> It would be wrong to think of Descartes
as a genuine skeptic.
He was the first of the rationalists and
claimed he employed hyperbolic doubt.
>> Hyperbolic means something like um
beyond any ordinary reason for doubt. It
is beyond any ordinary reason for doubt.
Precisely because it's calling into that
what's morally certain, and what's
morally certain, by definition,
is beyond all reasonable doubt. It's an
unreasonable doubt.
>> For Descartes, to perceive, [music] to
seem to see or hear something, is really
to think.
Since we know clearly and distinctly
about external objects through intuition
and the intellect, then the intellect
can know itself even more clearly and
distinctly.
Descartes uses the example of a piece of
wax.
The intellect perceives it as having
certain physical properties.
When the wax melts, these properties
disappear. [music]
Yet it is still wax, even though it is
now, as he says, something extended,
flexible, [music] and movable.
Extension is the key factor.
>> The case of the mutability of the of the
wax, that famous passage toward the end
[music] of the second meditation,
one of the things that that
illustrates for Descartes
is that what we call the secondary or
sensory properties of physical objects
are, on his view, fundamentally confused
properties. They're not properties that
can be fully grasped by the intellect.
And so, if we were empiricists and
believed that
our knowledge of external objects comes
entirely through their sensory
properties, for Descartes that would be
like a council of despair, because it
would amount to admitting that we can't
actually have a proper intellectual
grasp of objects in the world around us.
But,
rather than advocate such a council,
Descartes,
by focusing on extension as being of the
essence of physical objects,
uh,
gives an account of our knowledge of
physical objects that
conforms to his conception of what the
intellect does because the properties
associated with extension, as James
said, are susceptible of a geometrical
and more generally mathematical
analysis. And these are properties which
on Descartes's view and
in a way that's also amenable to common
sense, are sort of proper
objects of the understanding in a way
that sensory prop- properties like
colors and and and smells and tastes and
so forth are not.
>> In Meditations, Descartes gives two
proofs for the existence of God.
In Descartes's view, we must show that
God is the cause of the idea we have of
him.
This idea is not something we have made
up ourselves.
>> Descartes presents in the Meditations
three arguments for the existence of
God. Some people think there are only
two.
Um, I think there are three. Two of them
are what are called cosmological
arguments based on conceptions of
causation in the third meditation.
Um, and in those arguments Descartes
claims that only God is a sufficiently
powerful being to have caused the idea
of God in our minds.
Uh, and also the second argument is that
only God is sufficiently powerful to
have caused the existence of our minds
given that our minds contain the idea of
God.
These arguments are based on somewhat
obscure scholastic terminology, in
particular the distinction between
formal and real a formal and objective
reality.
Uh, and for these and other reasons,
they're not really taken seriously as
candidates for establishing the
existence of God by philosophers these
days.
The story with his third argument for
the existence of God, the ontological
argument in the fifth meditation, is
rather different because in that
argument he argues that God must exist
on the basis of the nature of the
concept of God alone. That is it's part
of the real nature of of God that
he must have all perfections and
existence is a perfection and he must
therefore exist just as it's part of the
the nature of a triangle to have
interior angles adding up to two two
right angles.
>> For Descartes, [music]
the existence of God was linked to the
knowledge of science.
Extension [music] is the essential
nature of matter.
Knowledge of it comes from geometry.
This gives us knowledge of the objective
properties of things.
All science depends upon the knowledge
alone of the true God.
By the sixth meditation, [music]
Descartes still didn't believe he had
proved that material things exist.
>> [music]
>> He knew they could exist in so far as
they were considered as objects of
geometrical proof.
Also, our imagination persuades us that
material things exist.
>> [music]
>> God can produce anything we can conceive
exactly as we conceive it.
Descartes then moved on to try and
answer the question, "What am I?"
It is certain [music] that I am entirely
and truly distinct from my body and can
exist apart from it.
>> The point really about saying that mind
and body are really are really distinct
is that
um
it follows that God could keep the the
the mind, that is to say the rational
soul, the soul,
>> [snorts]
>> in existence after the body dies
and consequently
the possibility of the immortality of
the soul is actually demonstrated by
showing that mind and body are really
distinct.
It's not that it show it's shown that
the soul is immortal, but it's at least
shown that it's possible that the soul
is immortal.
We can make sense of that possibility.
That's what's important to him about
um
the real distinction between mind and
body.
>> [snorts]
>> Um an interesting point to note there is
that the um
faculties of sense perception and
imagination
are tied in a way to the body, although
they are modes of thinking and hence
belong to the mind. They belong only to
embodied minds.
And if we then try to even conceive of
what it would be like, so to speak, to
be
the rational soul after the death of the
body,
well, it's no longer going to have sense
perception and imagination. All it's got
is pure intellect. And in a sense, all
it's got to think about is objects of
the pure intellect,
which roughly speaking correspond to
geometry, arithmetic,
metaphysics, logic, and God.
So, it's going to be the existence of
the soul after the body dies is going to
be very different existence from the its
existence now.
But, as I say, the point of saying that
mind and body are really distinct is to
make the point that the soul can survive
the death death of the body.
>> Descartes did not think that everything
was a function of his own mind, but his
approach tends to be in that direction.
His views were to influence such people
as Isaac Newton, but he had his critics.
Another prominent critic was Blaise
Pascal, remembered for his famous wager.
God is or he is not.
But, to which side shall we incline?
Let us weigh the gains and loss in
wagering what God is.
Let us estimate the two chances.
If you gain, you gain all.
If you lose, you lose nothing.
Wager then without hesitation that he
is.
I have striven not to laugh at human
actions, not to weep at them, not to
hate them, but to understand them.
Spinoza was a Dutch Jew.
His parents had fled the Inquisition in
Portugal and settled in Amsterdam where
Spinoza was born in 1632.
He was brought up as an Orthodox Jew,
but soon grew skeptical.
He was excommunicated for his beliefs
and left Amsterdam in 1660.
He took a keen interest in science,
corresponding regularly with members of
the Royal Society in London.
Strangely, it is the lapsed Jew,
Spinoza, rather than the devout Catholic
Descartes, whose writing contains the
more religious element.
Like Aristotle and Plato, Spinoza was
concerned with how human beings can
attain the good.
>> Well, the good for Spinoza, or the state
which he describes as that of human
blessedness, is something to be achieved
through knowledge, through knowledge of
ourselves, knowledge of the world, and
knowledge of our relationship to the
world.
Spinoza thinks that knowledge is
something that comes in different
degrees or levels. So, at the lowest
kind of level, there's the knowledge we
gain in everyday experience, from the
things we read, from the people we talk
to.
And this kind of knowledge, although
Spinoza admits it's very useful, he
thinks that nonetheless it's pretty
unreliable.
However, he thinks it's possible,
through the use of our human reason,
to free ourselves from its errors and
illusions, and to arise to a higher kind
of knowledge, the kind of knowledge that
you find for instance in philosophy and
science.
But moreover, he thinks it's possible to
continue this process of rational
refinement, and finally to arrive at a
state of knowledge in which we have an
immediate and intuitive vision of the
connected whole that is the universe.
And this state, which Spinoza calls the
intellectual love of God, is he thinks
the highest state possible for a human
being. It's our supreme goal.
>> For Spinoza, the main function of God is
to be the first cause, by which he means
something like rationale.
In truth, there can be conceived only
one substance which is absolutely
independent, and that is God.
Except God, no substance can be granted
or conceived.
All things are in God, and God is the
immanent cause of all things.
God necessarily exists.
Spinoza allows the existence of any one
infinite substance, the cause of
everything else.
The human mind is simply part of the
infinite intellect of God.
Mind and body are essentially connected.
>> Well, Spinoza hoped to cut through all
of the problems that had beset his
predecessor, Descartes, concerning the
relationship between the mind and the
body through the very simple but bold
course of declaring them to be
identical,
the very same thing, not two but one.
They were, as you might say, two
different ways of looking at the same
thing,
the way something appears from the
outside, as it were,
and the way in which it's like to be
that thing.
Although that said, it needs to be
remembered that that's not quite right.
Because to say to talk of one reality
which could be taken or could be
understood in two different ways
suggests that perhaps it isn't really
either of them. And for Spinoza, reality
is very definitely something which can
be understood in both of these ways.
>> In the third part of Ethics, Spinoza
deals with the nature of emotions.
Freedom comes from an understanding of
oneself and one's emotions.
The greater that understanding, the
greater one's understanding of God.
Freedom becomes the acceptance of
absolute determinism.
We are all modifications of God or
nature.
Spinoza died in 1677 of consumption.
Most of his works were published
posthumously.
At first, they were greeted with
incomprehension.
It was only later that his contribution
to philosophy was fully appreciated.
>> Well, the poet Novalis described Spinoza
as God-intoxicated.
And he's always appealed to those of a
religious, spiritual, even mystical
orientation.
On the other hand, he's also been very
popular with
people who emphasize human reason and
who are unhappy with the notion of the
supernatural because it's a very clear
consequence of Spinoza's philosophy that
nothing can ever interfere with the
system from outside. There are no
miracles.
So, perhaps Spinoza's greatest
contribution to philosophy is to suggest
a way in which these two seemingly
opposing views of the world can somehow
be reconciled together.
Because if he is a mystical philosopher,
he's nonetheless a thoroughly rational
mystic.
>> There is nothing without a reason.
Philosophy was in Leibniz's blood.
His father was a moral philosopher in
Leipzig.
Much of his life was spent in the
service of the House of Brunswick, and
he was commissioned to write its
history.
Surprisingly, he published only one book
of philosophy in his lifetime, the
Theodicy, a work on natural theology.
But he wrote many unpublished works,
>> [music]
>> the most important of which was the
Discourse on Metaphysics.
>> Apart from one book and a number of
occasional articles, the vast bulk of
Leibniz's material was unpublished
during his lifetime. And it is vast. The
catalog contains some 57,000
items.
Most of it consists in drafts and notes
and sketches. He seems to be one of
these kind of philosophers who thought
things out on paper. But a great deal of
it consists in correspondence. And much
of what he wrote was prepared for the
many individual scholars that he entered
into correspondence with.
This isn't perhaps so unusual in its
time. But of course, the loss to modern
scholarship is that there is no one
place that we can go to for any kind of
full or systematic account of his views.
>> Leibniz wanted to produce a universal
logical and mathematical language.
This would have made possible the
solution of a whole range of problems.
>> The problems that would have been solved
if such a goal was attainable
are mostly to do with avoiding the sorts
of errors that one runs into when one's
language is ambiguous or where the
meaning of words is not clear, is
imprecise, and so on.
>> According to this plan, all knowledge
would be fundamentally
a matter of definition, and therefore it
would be possible to settle any dispute
by consultation to some kind of
universal encyclopedia or dictionary.
It needs to be remembered that this
project belongs really to the earliest
phase of Leibniz's career, and as his
thought progressed, it was either
abandoned or at least relegated to a
back seat. But it remains important
because the vision of knowledge as an
interconnected whole, as well as the
certain amount of the logical apparatus
that was developed for the scheme, these
things continued to influence his
philosophy throughout his career.
>> Leibniz believed that the world consists
of substances he called monads.
He developed his theory in a work
entitled Monadology.
Although Leibniz was a rationalist, his
theories also made allowance for the use
of common sense.
He agreed with Aristotle that substances
[music]
were the basic things that made up the
universe,
but he believed that these substances
[music] must be absolutely simple.
Leibniz believed that this world was
just one of an infinite set of worlds
God could have created.
Leibniz describes [music] these worlds
as compossible, meaning that their
components must fit together.
The world God chooses to create is the
best compossible one.
God had so created the world that
everything that was true of a substance
[music]
was necessarily true of it because it
followed from its individual essence.
Leibniz also believed in the principle
that he called the principle of
sufficient reason.
>> The principle of sufficient reason says
that for every truth, there must be a
reason why it's so and not otherwise, or
what Leibniz takes to be equivalent,
that everything has a cause.
What it rules out is the possibility
that certain things might just happen or
be for no reason whatsoever. Now, we may
not know what that reason or cause is,
says Leibniz, but nonetheless we can be
assured that there must be one.
Principle of sufficient reason is very
controversial principle that has and
indeed continues to divide philosophers.
>> Antoine Arnauld attacked Leibniz's
theory.
If God had programmed Adam to fall,
there was no room for freedom.
Leibniz argued that freedom, causal
determinism, and logical determinism
were all different.
After 40 years of faithful service with
the House of Brunswick, Leibniz fell out
of favor with his master, England's
[music] future King George I.
He died in Hanover in 1716.
>> [music]
>> John Locke was the son of a West Country
lawyer who had supported Parliament
during the Civil War.
Locke was part of a movement that came
to be called British empiricism.
He entered the service of the first Earl
of Shaftesbury.
In 1683, when his master [music] seemed
in danger of being impeached for
treason, Locke went with him to the
Netherlands.
Locke spent 6 years there.
Once William of Orange had replaced
James II on the English throne, he felt
it safe to return.
It was during his self-imposed exile
that Locke wrote his Essay Concerning
Human Understanding.
Locke tries to define what he means by
the term idea.
That term, which I think, serves to
stand for whatsoever is the object of
the understanding when a man thinks.
In book one of the essay, Locke attacks
the view that there are innate
principles such as identity and
contradiction and principles of morals.
Many people believed in such principles
[music] because they believed they were
universally acceded to.
Locke denies this.
He believed only that there might be
innate capacities.
In book two, Locke has a simple answer
to the question, "Where do ideas come
from?"
In one word,
from experience.
Experience does this in two ways,
through sensation and through
reflection.
>> We form ideas from sensation and
reflection by a combination of
noticing the resemblance among the ideas
we get from our senses
and by
abstracting and recombining
ideas to form more complex ones.
So, it's possible to form the idea of
an animal that you've never seen, like a
unicorn,
by putting together
ideas that are directly derived from
things you have seen, like that of
horses and horns.
>> Locke also distinguishes between simple
and complex ideas.
He takes it for granted that his reader
will know what a simple idea is.
Later philosophers, such as
Wittgenstein, showed that there were no
such things as simple ideas in the sense
that Locke taught.
Yet, it was a concept at the very center
of empiricism itself.
Locke classified complex ideas in terms
of their objects,
substances, modes, and relations.
>> Substances for
things that exist in the world,
material objects.
thought that the best guess as to what
the ultimate substance was was that it
was extended stuff.
Matter, but atoms, made up of atoms.
Modes are just what we would now call
properties.
They're ways in which substances can be.
And relations are other involving
properties such as
being to the left of or being heavier
than.
>> When he published his fourth edition of
the essay in 1700, Locke offered a
different basis for classifying ideas.
Locke made an important distinction
between primary and secondary qualities
when dealing with the simple ideas of
sense.
>> Locke famously made a distinction
between primary and secondary qualities,
but he wasn't the first to make this
distinction. It's made by Galileo. It's
also made by the ancient Greek atomists.
The idea is roughly to distinguish
between the properties of things which
they really have
and the properties which they only
appear to have.
So, for example,
imagine three bowls of water, one of
which is cold, one of which is
lukewarm, and one of which is hot.
If you put your hand in the hot bowl and
then the lukewarm one, the lukewarm one
feels cold. You put your hand in the
cold one and then the lukewarm one, the
lukewarm one feels hot.
Hence, it's argued that the hotness of
the water is not a property it has in
reality, but merely a property that it
has in so far as it appears to you.
>> It seems that Locke often failed to heed
his own advice as laid down in book
four.
Locke also wrote two treatises on civil
government.
The principles laid [music] were to
influence the drafting of the American
Constitution.
Man being by nature all free, equal, and
independent, no one can be put out of
this estate and subjected to the
political power of another without his
own consent.
But everyone has the right to punish
everyone for the evil he has done.
Everyone has the executive power of the
law of nature.
Locke's view of the state of nature
differs sharply from Hobbes.
All men have an obligation to the other
members of society.
In Locke's ideal state, there is no
absolute sovereign.
Land and animals are common to all men,
but become an individual's private
property when he uses them.
The purpose of his treaty on civil
government was to defend the Glorious
Revolution of 1688, and many of his
ideas are not always practical.
Yet his ideas can be said to have laid
the foundations for Western democracy.
>> [music]
>> Truth is the cry of all, but the game of
the few.
George Berkeley was born in [music]
Kilkenny and became Bishop of Cloyne.
He is perhaps best remembered for his
theory that material exists only as
ideas in the mind.
To be
is to be perceived.
Dr. Johnson famously ridiculed this by
kicking a stone.
I refute it thus.
Berkeley's theories are based around
immediate perception
that we first perceive the proper
objects of the senses, such as light,
sound, smell, and taste. [music]
He assumes that these sensations are
ideas.
This idea is similar to that of
Aristotle.
As Berkeley made clear, not all ideas
are sensations, but all sensations are
ideas.
He often uses the terms interchangeably.
Locke had asserted that the secondary
qualities of an object were subjective.
For instance, when we are near a fire,
we may feel pain.
Is it the idea of warmth produced by the
fire, although the pain is in us?
This fails to distinguish between warmth
and feelings of warmth.
Berkeley accepted Locke's argument, but
said that similar considerations applied
to primary qualities as well.
Berkeley's first work, Theory of Vision,
is a work on optics.
He also included in it extracts from
Descartes' Dioptrics.
Berkeley believed that the retina of the
eye was a two-dimensional surface. It
was impossible for the third dimension
to be projected onto it.
A man named Molyneux had once raised the
question, if a man born blind were to
gain his sight, would he immediately
perceive things as at a distance?
Berkeley's answer was no.
He said the man would need experience to
connect the ideas of sight with the
ideas of touch.
Berkeley saw himself as a man of common
sense.
He seems to have been unruffled by the
ridicule of men such as Swift and
Johnson.
He held God to be the author of nature,
whose existence is evident in the ideas
he produces.
>> Berkeley's conception of God places him
quite squarely in the tradition of
Descartes and Malebranche, in the sense
that, well, and ultimately Plato,
in the sense that for for Berkeley, God
is the supreme ground of of being and of
intelligibility and of perceptibility.
So, Berkeley thinks this
the role of God is to really sustain
everything in existence.
Uh and because Berkeley thinks that to
be is to be perceived, uh he he believes
that
to sustain thing well, to be is to be
perceived or to perceive.
So, where ideas are concerned,
uh I entities whose being consists in
their being perceived, if God is
sustaining them in existence, he's doing
so by
uh ensuring that they are continuously
perceptible.
Um and that's why for Berkeley,
uh
objects in the external world, and he
does think there is such a thing as an
external world, he just thinks it's
composed of ideas rather than material
substances,
objects in the exten- external world do
continue to exist even when we're not
perceiving them, but only by courtesy of
their being
uh continuously perceived by God.
>> [music]
[music]
>> David Hume was born into a family of
poor landed gentry in Edinburgh in 1711.
One of Hume's major concerns was the
relationship between cause and effect,
causality.
It was and still is important not only
to Hume, but [music] to philosophy
generally, because without an
understanding of it, the universe
consists of random, unconnected events.
Understanding causality not only means
making sense of the world we live in,
but our place in it as well, and our
experiences.
Hume started with attempts to prove the
existence of God and the self.
Hume claimed we must have observational
evidence and experience of God and the
self.
But we have no direct experience of God.
We cannot hear, see, touch, or
experience God in any tangible way.
Feeling that God must somehow exist is
not enough.
>> Hume is a skeptic as far as religion is
concerned. Um because the mind operates
through custom.
Um and uh is there is this kind of
cement through habit and association. It
can only work on material that has been
received through the senses.
Because there is no impression of God or
of anything beyond this world, um we
can't appropriately extend the abstract
ideas that we think we have but are just
these bundles to the realm of the
religious. So there's an attack on
religion which is very strong. Um
and really one of the things that he
argues is that all priests are
necessarily hypocrites because they have
to disguise to themselves their
unbelief. Um and he doesn't go as far as
to deny that God exists but through the
mouth of various characters he
undermines belief in a first cause, uh
in God as a a substance, in the soul as
a unity, and in immortality of the soul.
>> Hume concludes that in order for us to
have any knowledge of a supreme being is
to witness an action that transgresses
the laws of nature as it is only through
the world that God as an infinite being
can express his nature and make himself
felt.
So God makes his presence known through
miracles.
Hume claimed that like God and the self,
we cannot observe causal connection.
>> For Hume, causality is just um a
a succession of ideas, a contiguity of
ideas,
which are then linked together by the
mind. And you can't actually find the
necessity in nature. It's something that
the mind adds in on top.
>> This holds true even with things that
[music] seem certain, like night
following day.
Day is not the cause of night. Night is
brought on by the rotation of the Earth
on its axis as it travels around the
Sun.
We cannot observe this rotation, so how
can we be completely sure that night
will follow day?
Can we get beyond conjunction of events
to actually observing their causes?
Can we distinguish between events that
are causally connected to those that are
not?
If we cannot, how can we make any
statements about the world?
Where does this leave science?
>> He doesn't He's not attacking science.
As I said, [music]
he thinks of himself as a Newton of the
mind. It's just that science and the
connections in science have to be
explained psychologically
instead of in terms of logical and
philosophical relations.
>> Hume had an answer to this seemingly
bleak scenario.
Although he advises we should hold our
opinions with a healthy dose of
skepticism,
Hume was realistic about what drives
human beings and the role played by the
emotions.
If we did try to live our lives querying
everything we saw and stubbornly
refusing to go about our daily lives
because we do not know anything for
certain, we would all curl up and die.
It is better to be proved wrong
sometimes in our assumptions than to
abstain from doing anything at all.
>> [music]
>> So, act as to treat humanity whether in
thine own person or that of any other
in every case as an end with all, never
as means only.
Immanuel Kant is the giant of
18th-century philosophy.
Many would argue he was the greatest
philosopher ever.
In 1781, he published his Critique of
Pure Reason.
He followed this with two further
critiques
on practical reason and judgment.
[music]
He also wrote on religion, politics, and
psychology.
Though all our knowledge begins with
experience, it does not follow that it
all arises out of experience.
Kant did not even accept the
empiricists' theory that all ideas arose
out of experience.
>> Well, he agreed with the empiricists in
that he
um thought that all our knowledge all
our
substantive knowledge about the world
must ultimately relate to experience,
which is a basic empiricist theme.
Um and he was
sure that they were right about that. Uh
he was as
uh reluctant as they were to uh
countenance the idea of
conclusions about things that utterly
transcended our experience. Um
for example, he had no patience at all
with attempts to prove the existence of
a transcendent God um or with uh
speculations uh about
an afterlife, for example, what might
happen to us after our deaths.
When these were understood as attempts
to come again at substantive knowledge,
I mean, he didn't feel that we could
have knowledge about these things at
all. Um he was sympathetic to
attempts to think in those terms and to
speculate about those things, but he was
of a
mind with the empiricists in denying
that we could know anything about those
realities beyond our experience.
So, in that sense, he was he was very
much in line with them as against the
rationalists.
He He agreed that um all our knowledge
must ultimately relate to experience and
be grounded in experience.
Um
but he didn't think that it was all
simply read off from experience.
He thought that when we uh derive
knowledge of the world through the
deliverances of experience, it was
because we ourselves were appropriately
receptive to what was out there.
And being appropriately receptive meant
having certain faculties in terms of
which we interpreted what was out there.
Certain faculties that enabled us to
make sense of what was out there.
Um and the analogy that is often used in
this connection, it's not Kant's own
analogy, but it's quite a useful
analogy, is
that it's as if we were operating with a
pair of spectacles of epistemological
spectacles, um
through which we interpret
what the world throws at us, as it were.
Um
but these spectacles
um
are unlike ordinary spectacles in that
we can never take them off. I mean,
everything that we know
we know through this basic framework.
They provide a kind of of structure for
for what we know, a a framework, as I
say, through through which we interpret
things. Um
That is where the element of idealism
lies, um because we ourselves are making
a contribution to shape of our
experiences.
The reason why Kant wanted to call it
transcendental idealism, so it is a
special kind of idealism, was that we
could never take our spectacles off.
There was no such thing as as taking our
specs off and stepping back and looking
at this process as it was in itself. Uh
we were always constrained to see things
through this basic framework.
And that's why um he felt that it was
appropriate to to distance himself, for
example, from from Berkeley, whose view
was also, obviously, an idealist view,
um but um who felt that the the
idealistic processes that were giving us
knowledge were themselves things that we
could reflect on and and come to know
about.
>> Kant later attempted to justify the
various principles according to [music]
which objective experience must be
organized.
In the section of the critique of pure
reason called the dialectic, Kant
explores his own theory of ideas, which
[music] are pure concepts of reason.
Because we have reason, we naturally
have these ideas.
Kant also dealt with ethics and morals.
Nothing in the world, indeed nothing
[music] even beyond the world, can
possibly be conceived which can be
called good without qualification,
except a good will.
>> What Kant means by a good will is a will
that's exercised in complete accord with
its own freedom. That's to say a will
that is in in a popular phrase that's
often used in this connection, a will
that's a law unto itself. It's following
its own principles, its own rules, its
own laws.
Um
And those laws, Kant believes, he has
all sorts of interesting arguments to
substantiate these this belief. Those
laws are the laws of morality.
A good will is a will that acts on
principle purely for the sake of
principle,
doing what it does
simply because that's the right and
proper thing to do. That's the the
law-governed thing to do. And doing that
in turn simply because it's acting in
accord with its own laws. That is to say
it's acting in a way that's completely
autonomous and free.
So, a good will is a will that's um
if you like
obeying the laws of its own freedom.
And that has uh important resonances for
Kant because that in turn is is a will
that is
completely moral in its
in its determinations, in its behavior,
in in in the behavior that it causes.
>> In the Critique of Judgment, Kant
explores how our aesthetic judgments
depend upon the interplay of imagination
and understanding.
Kant lived for [clears throat] 80 years,
but never married.
During that time, he never strayed far
from his native Königsberg, but his
philosophy was to influence the whole
world.
>> In modern philosophy, Kant's influence
is second only to that of Descartes. So,
it the defining moment of the
beginning of modern philosophy is
Descartes' Meditations, then
the defining moment of later modern
philosophy is Kant's Critique of Pure
Reason.
And
Kant's influence is
in the 19th century, he spawns a whole
idealistic, romantic movement in
philosophy
unintentionally.
In the 20th century, he's very
influential in ethics, but also in
political theory.
>> I mean, he's had an absolutely immense
influence um in in general and
specifically on on subsequent
philosophers.
His his general influence um
is has to do with um the various
enlightenment ideals that he championed.
He's a major figure in the enlightenment
and and we all know what kind of an
influence that in turn had.
He helped to put reason back on the map.
He was um able to to to champion reason
and to give um a compelling account of
of how much reason is able to achieve,
how much human beings are able to
achieve through the use of reason,
through being purely rational,
which is obviously a a very important
enlightenment theme.
And in particular in his views about
moral philosophy, um he was
able to
give a again a very compelling account
of
how far we're able to get in
distinguishing between right and wrong
simply by using our own natural,
rational resources
without having to appeal to
authority, and in particular without
having to appeal to the authority of
religion.
So, that's um a huge enlightenment
impact that he's that he's had. But also
specifically on philosophers, I mean,
there's
virtually no philosophy that has come
since in the 200 years since Kant died
that is not in some way been influenced
by Kant.
Very few people nowadays are
straightforward Kantians. It's not that
kind of influence. And
people that
see things in a very non-Kantian way
still recognize the force of his
arguments and and the strength of his
position and see it as something that
they have to respond to. So, he's pretty
much shaped the
the whole nature of subsequent
philosophical discussion,
set the parameters, determined what it
is that people feel that they have to
discuss, what the main issues are, what
the main questions are that need to be
addressed.
>> As the 19th century dawned and the
Industrial Revolution changed the nature
of society forever, philosophical
thinking would begin to take a new turn.
Established beliefs would be challenged.
>> [music]
[music]